<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The most humble remonstrances presented to the Honourable the knights, citizens, and burgesses of the House of Commons, in Parliament assembled</title>
            <author>Chabbert, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78509</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1784A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205737</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899812</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899812</idno>
            <idno type="VID">135389</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78509)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135389)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2456:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The most humble remonstrances presented to the Honourable the knights, citizens, and burgesses of the House of Commons, in Parliament assembled</title>
                  <author>Chabbert, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By John Chabbert, whose name appears on p. 2.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Huguenots --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Poor --  Services for --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:135389:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE Moſt Humble Remonſtrances PRESENTED</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>To the Honourable the</hi> Knights, Citizens, <hi>and</hi> Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes <hi>of the</hi> HOUSE of COMMONS, <hi>in</hi> Parliament <hi>Aſſembled.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. COncerning the Proofs, whereby the <hi>French</hi> Gentlemen Commiſſioners, appointed for the Diſtribution of the Charity beſtowed upon the Poor <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants that are come for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge into <hi>England;</hi> may be convinced, that in their Hands, there are ſtill remaining great Summs of Money, ariſing from the ſaid Charity, and a Revenue more than ſufficient for all the Poor Refuges Maintenance.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Concerning the Means, whereby all the aforeſaid great Summs of Money may be diſcovered, and the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid <hi>French</hi> Gentlemen Commiſſioners compelled to give an exact account of them, which compelling (if it pleaſe God) ſhall be, as a triumphing Sword Cutting, with one Blow, the Gordian Knot of the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Concerning the Motives, that may induce the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Honourable Houſe of Commons to uſe the aforeſaid means; which Motives are the Concerns of the King and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:135389:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>State in general, and in particular of all the Poor amongſt the ſaid Refuges.</p>
            <p>By <hi>John Chabbert</hi> Miniſter and Refuge.</p>
            <p>You the Honourable Houſe of Commons are intreated by the aforeſaid <hi>John Chabbert,</hi> to approve, that he may now declare to your Honours, the love he hath and ever had for Juſtice and Truth; and on the contrary, how he abhorreth Injuſtice, Cheating Tricks, and Lies: But in a particular manner, how much he longs for the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage and proſperity of the King, State, and Church of <hi>England,</hi> not only for the Publick's, but alſo for the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate's ſake; as he longs alſo for the ſatisfaction of the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Poor, as well as of them which are amongſt the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuges; and that in making bold humbly to ſhew, by par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, all the Contents of the three Heads contained in the Title of his Undertaking.</p>
            <p>To keep the order ſet in the ſaid Title; the aforeſaid <hi>John Chabbert</hi> beginning with the aforeſaid Proofs humbly ſheweth,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the aforeſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners have receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed great Summs of Money, upon three ſeveral Letters Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents heretofore granted by Royal Authority, for the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Poor Refuges ſake; eſpecially upon the firſt and ſecond Letters Pattents, the firſt granted in the Year 1686. and the ſecond granted in the Year 1688. That after that the ſaid two Letters Pattents were effectually publiſhed, and the Tenor of the ſame declared unto the Nation, in all and every Church and Chappel in the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> Dominion of <hi>Wales, &amp;c.</hi> The whole Nation was touched with ſo deep a ſenſe and tender Commiſeration of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities and woful Sufferings of the ſaid Poor Refuges, in the cauſe of their Religion, and of the urgent neceſſity, which ſo many of them were lying under, that, not only,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:135389:2"/>all the Nobility, Gentry, and every Rich Man, of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Degree and Character ſoever he was; But even the greateſt part of all the Tradeſmen and Servants, as every body knows, did ſo generouſly and chearfully contribute, by their extraordinary and large Charities, to the ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> amongſt the Refuges; and that from thoſe generous, free, and large Charitable Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions, which have been made for the relief of the ſaid poor Refuges, it muſt needs be inferred, that great Sums of Money were then Collected.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the aforeſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners and the Miniſters, and Church-wardens, or Elders, as they call them, of the <hi>French</hi> Church in the <hi>Savoy,</hi> or of the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loon Church in the City of <hi>London,</hi> have received great Summs of Money, from the large Charities of particular Collections, often beſtowed, by a great many Charitable Perſons, upon the aforeſaid Poor Refuges behalf, from the beginning of the Year 1685. to this very day of the Year 1696. Since that time a great number of Poor Refuges have been ſeen in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That the aforeſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, Miniſters, and Church-wardens of the aforeſaid two Churches, very often, and at leaſt, during the ſpace of Ten Years, have received great Summs of Money, ariſing from a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Legacies, the moſt part of them made by ſome <hi>Engliſh</hi> pious Perſons, and ſome of them by ſome <hi>French,</hi> to be diſtributed in a very ſhort time, after their Deceaſe to the ſaid Poor Refuges: But that it is to be feared, the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, have diſtributed nothing of the moſt part of the ſaid Legacies, or at leaſt, but the uſe, or intereſt of ſome of them, to the ſaid Poor Refuges; ſo that, when this third Proof, as well as the ſecond before is duly reflected upon; it plainly appears by the ſaid two
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:135389:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>Proofs, that they muſt needs have in their own, or others Hands a great Fund of Money for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſupport of the poor Refuges.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That the aforeſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, by their own Confeſſion, and as every body knows, have received, during the ſpace of many Years <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Twelve Thouſand Pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> beſtowed liberally, chearfully and charitably, by His excellent Majeſty our gracious King <hi>William,</hi> upon the ſaid Poor Refuges, to relieve them in their urgent neceſſities, and comfort them in their trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. That it is moſt certain, that upon the ſaid Royal Bounty, the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, during the ſpace of the many Years aforeſaid, were able to ſupply all the wants of the ſaid Poor Refuges, if they had very well managed the ſaid Twelve Thouſand Pounds <hi>per Annum,</hi> or if they had not kept back ſome of them, or put them into Bankers Hands, or imployed ſome of them in Trading and Traffick.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That the aforeſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners were pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly Accuſed, by ſome of the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Refuges, Poor Gentlemen, Miniſters and others, for having embezzelled, or miſ-imployed a conſiderable Summ of the aforeſaid Twelve Thouſand Pounds <hi>Per Annum:</hi> And that the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners have done their utmoſt endeavours to ſecure themſelves from the ſaid Accuſation, or rather, that their Accuſers ſhould be ſilent, and deſiſt from their Accuſation; And for all that, the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners have let neither the Publick, nor their Accuſers know their Innocence, in all its Circumſtances; and in keeping the Formalities of Juſtice, although they were bound ſo to do for the ſecuring of their own Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:135389:3"/>
            <p n="6">6. That the aforeſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived ſome conſiderable Summs of Money, by the way of many Subſcriptions and private Collections, made in the City of <hi>London</hi> and its Suburbs, for the aforeſaid <hi>French</hi> Refuges Poor, yet for all that, it doth not appear, that, at leaſt, the greateſt part of the aforeſaid <hi>French</hi> Refuges Poor, was the more relieved, by the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners, than they were before the ſaid Subſcriptions and private Collections.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That the aforeſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, doubtleſs, have received, and do ſtill receive, a great many private Charities of particular Perſons, for the maintenance of many Charity-houſes, which Charity-houſes imperceptibly and cunningly have been ſet up, by the ſame Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners in the Suburbs of the aforeſaid City of <hi>London,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Years ago, upon four accounts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To procure, as many Charities as could be poſſible, and to move all the charitable Perſons, who live in the ſaid City of <hi>London,</hi> and other Cities and Towns of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, to put into their hands, all the Charities they had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned for all the Poor amongſt the Refuges, which are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to beg, and which were never partakers of the ſaid Charities, beſtowed upon the ſaid Charity-houſes, although they may be in great want.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To have a Lawful Cauſe, at leaſt, in appearance, to beg either themſelves, or move their Friends and Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſo to do, every where, and of every Perſon, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they believed to be the moſt favourable to their Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity-houſes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To have a pretence, continually to declare openly, as they have done already, that they had received but very few private Charities for the ſupport of their Charity<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, and that they were obliged ſometimes, to turn
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:135389:4"/>out many of the ſaid Poor Refuges from the ſaid Charity<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, and to deprive many more of the Soup or Broth diſtributed therein, or to maintain them both with a Fund deſigned for paying of the Penſions to the <hi>French</hi> Poor Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, Miniſters, and other Perſons of what Age ſoever, and of both Sexes; the Penſions, of ſome of which ſaid Perſons, the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners leſſened upon ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral occaſions; although the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners were perſuaded, that before they had leſſened the ſaid Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the ſaid Poor Gentlemen, Miniſters, and other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuges, the ſaid Penſions were not ſufficient for their main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance. And beſides, although the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners were perſuaded, that the ſaid Poor Gentlemen, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and other Refuges, cannot live by any other means.</p>
            <p n="4">4. To caſt a miſt before the whole <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation's Eyes, and to hide from the Publick, the ſaid moſt conſiderable Fund, they have in their Hands, ariſing from the aforeſaid very large Charities, they have received for the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Refuges Poor's ſupport, and for no other uſe whatſoever.</p>
            <p n="8">8. That the aforeſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners have ſaved very much of the aforeſaid large Charities, they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, by the aforeſaid ſeveral ways: And that the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, Miniſters, and Church-Wardens of the <hi>French</hi> Church in the <hi>Savoy,</hi> and <hi>Walloon</hi>-Church in the City of <hi>London,</hi> have ſaved very much of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid great Summs of Money, by ſix ways, well known, to the greateſt part of the <hi>French</hi> Refuges.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In keeping ſome of the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Refuges, lying then under a great neceſſity, from the leaſt Relief, which the tender hearted, and generous <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation had af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded to them, as well as to the reſt of the Refuges, who were then, or are ſtill relieved, by which means ſome of the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, as themſelves, together
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:135389:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>with all the Refuges know very well, were very near receiving an affront from ſome of thoſe ſaid neceſſitous Refuges, yet kept notwithſtanding from the ſaid Relief. Moreover, by this means a great many of the ſame Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuges, Poor and Helpleſs Creatures, were diſperſed all over <hi>England,</hi> and went a Begging up and down the ſaid Kingdom.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In giving once for all to ſome others of the ſaid Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuges a little Money, nay, and to ſome of the ſame more than to others, not according to every one's Deſert or Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, but according to their own Will and Pleaſure, againſt all Equity and Reaſon.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In giving to the ſmalleſt Number of the ſaid Poor Refuges a little Penſion, and that ſometimes only, for a little while, to thoſe who have no Friends amongſt them, or a powerful Protector who hath the Right to Command them: As for example, a Yearly Penſion of Seven Pounds, allowed to the Miniſters then under Fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years of Age, during the ſpace, at leaſt, of one Year and a half, is an evident Proof of the ſaid little Penſion, as well 56 <hi>l.</hi> 18 <hi>s.</hi> that every one of the ſaid Miniſters have received of the Royal Charity for their own and their Families Subſiſtance, during the ſpace of Nine years, as may be ſeen in a printed Paper delivered unto the King's Majeſty, the laſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>January,</hi> by all the poor Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters Refuges.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In paying the Penſion, as uſually they have payed it to the aforeſaid Poor Refuges; ſometimes Five, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Six, Seven, Eight, Nine; nay and ſometimes even Ten Months, after the Time appointed for the Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſaid Pention, inſtead of paying it Quarter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and even before hand; as it was in their Power ſo to do, having ever had, ſince their Commiſſion a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:135389:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>Fund for that purpoſe, whatever Aſſeverations they have made, to make the Publick, and the ſaid Poor Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuges believe the contrary. And the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, in paying Quarterly the ſaid Penſion, would have ſaved the ſaid Refuges from being ſo Poor, and a great many Troubles and Tears.</p>
            <p n="5">5. In utterly debarring the ſaid Poor Refuges from their own Penſion, during the ſpace of about Two Years, unjuſtly pretending, they had no Fund at all to pay it them; wherefore, many of the ſaid helpleſs Refuges, have contracted many Debts that they cannot pay off, without an Extraordinary Relief.</p>
            <p n="6">6. By the Deceaſe of a great many of the ſaid Poor Refuges, of all Ages whatſoever, of both Sexes, and of all Characters: That by theſe Six Ways and Means, the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners undoubtedly have ſaved very much of the ſaid very large Charitys they have received for the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Refuges Support. But nevertheleſs, the ſaid firſt Five Ways are Unlawful, and againſt the Rules of the Holy Goſpel; ſeeing by the ſaid Five Ways, a great many Poor Refuges, have been brought to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, to Hunger, and to Divers Temptations, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them have ſunk under them, as may eaſily be proved, by a great many Eye-Witneſſes; and that the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners themſelves, every where have Publiſhed, and often Declared to the Supreme Powers, that the ſaid Refugees have lain under great Poverty and Sufferings; the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, making a ſhow of being troubled at the ſaid Poor Refuges Calamities.</p>
            <p n="9">9. That the aforeſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, have ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much increaſed the ſaid Summs, ariſing from the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry large Charitys aforementioned, and they have increaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:135389:5"/>the ſaid Summs, either by all their following ways or by others, ſuch as theſe are.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Either in putting a good part of the ſaid Summs into a Bankers Hands, ſince the beginning of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, till this time.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Or in imploying another part of the ſaid Summs, in Trading, making the beſt of it by Sea and Land; either in this, or in Foreign Country's.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Or in erecting ſome Manufactures, to help off with another part of the ſaid Summs, coming from the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid very large Charity's, beſtowed upon the ſaid Poor Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuges; or in imploying it in ſome ſort of Commodities, that are the moſt <hi>a la mode,</hi> and do take the beſt.</p>
            <p n="10">10. That Mr. <hi>Daillon</hi> a <hi>French</hi> Miniſter Refuge, now one of the beſt Friends, that the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners may have, cannot deny; but that formerly, he undertook to oblige the ſame Gentlemen, <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, to give an Account of all the Summs of Money, or a part of them, ariſing from the Large General and Particular Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity's, upon all the Poor amongſt the Refuges; which ſaid Summs, came all into the Hands of the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, from the beginning of the Year 1696. Seeing that Undertaking was known by the Publick. I mean, by the moſt part of the <hi>French</hi> Refuges. And that the ſaid Mr. <hi>Daillon,</hi> undoubtedly, hath not forgotten; that on <hi>July</hi> the 10th, 1696. He Writ a Letter againſt the <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, to the Meeting of <hi>French</hi> Miniſters ſitting then, in the <hi>French</hi> Church, at <hi>Hungerford</hi>-Market, againſt the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners; by which ſaid Letter, he plainly ſhewed, that the ſaid <hi>Erench</hi> Commiſſioners, were making the beſt of the Money, accruing from the Charity's, beſtowed to the ſaid Poor, amongſt the Refuges; either by putting it out into the Goldſmiths, or Bankers Hands; or
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:135389:6"/>in Trading with it by Sea; and that only for themſelves. And that the ſame Commiſſioners did pay, by the ſaid Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, accruing from the ſaid Charity's, all their own Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, their Sallary, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Again, that the ſaid Mr. <hi>Daillon,</hi> durſt not make Oath, that he hath not ſaid and done, what is aforementioned. Now if he had ſo bad a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, he would be Convicted of Perjury, by many Eye-Witneſſes, who particularly knew his Undertaking, againſt the <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners; and who heard the Contents of the ſaid Letter, when it was Read before the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Miniſters met together; in whoſe Meeting, was Preſident, Mr. <hi>Betoule,</hi> an Ancient Miniſter, amongſt the Refuges, one of the beſt Friends of the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, who kept the ſaid Letter, and who is now dead.</p>
            <p n="11">11. That the aforeſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, would not part with their Commiſſion, and leave the Sole Care of the ſaid Refuges Poor's Maintenance, to the City of <hi>London,</hi> or to the Clergy of the ſaid City, who would have taken the ſaid Care upon themſelves. That it is a Convincing Proof, that the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners feared thereby, that the great Summs of Money, they have in their Hands, ſhould be diſcovered, and in ſuch a Caſe, they feared the loſing forever, the Adminiſtration of the ſaid great Summs, and withall, the hope of being the Owners of them probably, not remembring, that the aforeſaid Summs, coming from Bountiful Charity's, beſtowed upon the ſaid Reſuges Poor, are a Devoted and Holy Thing, committed to their Truſt; and that they in Conſcience, are bound to give a ſtrict Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of it, to God and Man, both in this World, and in the World to come, whatſoever they may think, ſay, or do about it.</p>
            <p n="12">12. That, aſſoon, as the <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, ſhall be Commanded by You the Honourable Houſe of Commons;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:135389:6"/>either openly to Confeſs, that they have in their own Hands, the ſaid great Summs, or to ſhew the contrary, by the Juſtifying Papers, Writings, and Deeds, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, do not perform, whatever they are commanded. Moreover, if by the ſaid Papers, Writings, and Deeds, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It doth not appear clearly, that the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, have diſtributed, (not to the Rich <hi>French</hi> Refuges) but only to the Poor, all the ſaid Summs, accruing from all the aforeſaid Charity's and Legacies. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, if inſtead of juſtifying themſelves thereby, the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, rather make this Objection: That they could not give an exact Account of the ſaid Summs, ſeeing that a great many Refuges, of both Sexes, cannot Write, and beſides, they have not ſet down all the Relie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Refuges Names. It muſt be inferred from thence; that the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, Miniſters, and Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens, of the aforeſaid two Churches, have not acted Faithfully, and Righteouſly, but that they acted againſt their own Conſcience, to Deſraud the ſaid Poor Refuges, of the greateſt part of the ſaid Charity's, and to deceive the Lords Commiſſioners; by whom, all their ſaid Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts were to be Examined. And that therefore, it is certain, they have ſtill in their Hands, the aforeſaid great Summs, whereof they muſt be forced, to give a particular and exact Account.</p>
            <p n="13">13. That if it may pleaſe You, the Honourable Houſe of Commons, to examine all the Proofs, given before, there is no doubt, but it will be plainly ſeen, that there muſt needs be remaining in the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners Hands, a very conſiderable Fund, accruing from the ſaid General and Particular large Charity's, often beſtowed. That there is left a very conſiderable Fund, accruing from the good Husbandry, and from the ſaid great Summs of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:135389:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>Money, whereof the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners have made uſe. Again, if it may pleaſe You, the Honourable Houſe ſo Commons, after Your Honours have examined, all the ſaid Evidences, to proceed againſt the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners, and againſt the Miniſters and Church-Wardens of the aforeſaid two Churches, to force them to confeſs, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that they have the ſaid Fund in their own Hands, or that they have put it into other Mens Hands, or to Convict them of the ſame, by other more eaſie and demonſtrative, better and ſhorter Ways and Means, if ſuch ones may be found. The aforeſaid <hi>John Chabbert,</hi> ſhall make bold ſtill, Humbly to ſhew Your Honors, all theſe following Means, which he believeth the moſt proper for his Project. He therefore ſheweth,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That if it may pleaſe You, the Honourable Houſe of Commons, to take notice of all the aforeſaid Summs of Money, ariſing from the ſaid Charity's, beſtowed upon the ſaid Poor Refuges, which ſaid Summs, and Charitys, are come to the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners Hands, or to the ſaid Miniſters and Church-Wardens of the aforeſaid two Churches Hands, from the beginning of the Year 1681. to this very Day of this Month of the Year, 1696. And again, if it may pleaſe You, the Honourable Houſe of Commons, to order the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and Church Wardens, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Preſently to prepare themſelves to give an exact Account, by Particulars, of all the ſaid Summs, come to their Hands, from the beginning of the ſaid Year, 1685. to this very day of the ſaid Year, 1696. The ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, will not dare to Diſobey Your Honors Command. This firſt Means, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, muſt needs be put into Practice. That the Publick, and the ſaid Poor Refuges may hope, that the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, Miniſters, and Church-Wardens of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:135389:7"/>ſaid to Churches, will be infallibly convinced, that they have in their own Hands, or in thoſe of their Friends, a great Fund, and more than ſufficient, to maintain the ſaid Poor Refuges.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That, if it may pleaſe You, the Honourable Houſe of Commons, to chuſe ſuch a Number of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentlemen, as Your Honors ſhall pleaſe, ſuch as ſhall be, all of an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary Goodneſs, and Piety, Gentlemen, who love Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and ſuffer not themſelves to be corrupted with Bribes, Gentlemen, who are mindful of the Publick Concerns, and of thoſe of the Poor's. And if it may pleaſe Your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, to appoint for Commiſſioners, ſuch deſerving Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, to examine the Accounts, that muſt be given, by Particulars, and the Acquittances, Catalogues, and other Papers, that muſt be brought to them, by the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, Miniſters, and Church-Wardens of the ſaid two Churches. Undoubtedly, this ſecond means will be very uſeful, to find out the aforeſaid great Fund, accru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the aforeſaid large Charitty's beſtowed for the ſaid Poor Refuges Maintenance.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That, if it may pleaſe You, the Honourable Houſe of Commons; to Order Mr. <hi>Daillon,</hi> Mr. <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mmarc,</hi> Mr. <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Forent</hi> French Miniſters Refuges, to appear in their own Perſons, before the aforeſaid Honourable Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners; and order the ſaid four Miniſters Refuges, to deliver to them, their Memories and other Papers, they have, making mention of all, or of ſome part of the Summs of Money, accruing from the aforeſaid Charity's, and whereby it plainly, or but darkly appears, that the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioenrs, Miniſters, and Church Wardens of the ſaid two Churches, have Maliciouſly, and Unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly managed, the ſaid great Summs of Money, and alienated ſome of them, or at leaſt, deprived the ſaid Poor
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:135389:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>Reſuges, of them. And again, if it may pleaſe Your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, to make the ſaid Poor Miniſters Refuges, Swear, and Declare by word of Mouth, before the ſaid Honourable Commiſſioners, whatever they know of the ſaid great Summs of Money, accruing from the aforeſaid Charities and Legacies, and whatever may be fit and proper any way to Convict the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, and the ſaid Miniſters and Church-wardens of the ſaid two Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of having in their Hands the aforeſaid great Fund, ariſing from the ſaid Charities and Legacies.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That, if it may pleaſe you, The Honourable Houſe of Commons, to oblige the ſame <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, Miniſters, and Church-wardens of the ſaid two Churches, to give up their Accounts, and preſently to produce, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the aforeſaid Honourable Commiſſioners, all the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quittances, all the Catalogues, and other Papers, wherein are written the Names of all the aforeſaid Poor Refuges, who received any thing of the ſaid great Summs, put into the Hands of the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Church-wardens, to be diſtributed to all the ſaid Poor amongſt the Refuges, from the beginning of the Year 1685 to this very Day <add rend="onBlank">26</add> of this Month <add rend="onBlank">no 6</add> of this Year 1696. It will plainly appear by this fourth means, that the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> have ſtill in their Hands a great Fund, and more than ſufficient, for the ſupport of the Poor amongſt the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuges.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That, if it may pleaſe you, the Honourable Houſe of Commons, not to give Ear to any kind of Reaſon, whereby the aforeſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, Miniſters and Church-wardens of the ſaid two Churches, either can, nor dare pretend to diſpenſe themſelves from giving an Account of the aforeſaid great Summs; But rather,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:135389:8"/>if it may pleaſe your Honours to ſhut your Ears to any that can, or may, be ſpoken in the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, Miniſters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> behalf, till the ſame have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in, and juſtified all their Accounts before the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Honourable Commiſſioner. 'Tis certain, that by this fifth means, the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, Miniſters and Church-wardens of the ſaid two Churches will be put to a <hi>non-plus,</hi> and forced to confeſs, that they have a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conſiderable Fund, accruing from the aforeſaid great Summs, and large Charities and Legacies, in ſpite of the beſt endeavours they have uſed, to make all the ſupreme Powers of this Kingdom, together with the Publick, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that they never had a Fund, that, at leaſt, would be ſufficient for the ſaid Poor Refuges maintainance, as it can be proved, by the troubleſome Petitions oftentimes preſented to the ſaid ſupreme Powers, by the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That, if it may pleaſe you, the Honourable Houſe of Commons, after the aforeſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, Miniſters and Church-wardens of the ſaid two Churches Accounts had been given up, and the aforeſaid Acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances, the aforeſaid Catalogue, and other Papers, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Names of all the Poor Relieved Refuges are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten down, examined by the aforeſaid Honourable Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners: If, I ſay, it may pleaſe your Honours, to Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in, to appear before the ſaid Honourable Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners, all the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Refuges, whoſe Name, or Hand may be ſeen in the ſaid Acquittances, Catalogues, and other Papers; that the ſaid Honourable Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners may take notice, if it be true, that all the ſaid Poor Refuges, have been ſo much, and ſo often relieved, and after that manner as is ſaid by the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners, and the ſaid Miniſters and Church-wardens of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:135389:9"/>ſaid two Churches: It will appear by this ſixth means, that there is ſtill a great Fund remaining in the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners Hands, and in the Hands of ſuch; who are favourers of their Party.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That, if it may pleaſe you, the Honourable Houſe of Commons to make the ſame <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, Miniſters and Church-wardens of the aforeſaid two Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, Swear to every thing they ſhall ſay as true, for their Juſtification, or for denying all the aforeſaid Fund, or a part of it; And to make them Swear beſides, to all the circumſtances of every thing, that they had ſaid, and will ſay. That the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, Miniſters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſeeing they are followed ſo cloſe, by this ſeventh means, without doubt, will confeſs, that they have ſtill in their own Hands, or in the Hands of others, at leaſt, a good part of the ſaid Fund, fearing to be declared per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured and utterly ruined in their Reputation, if they ſhould be Convicted of perjury, as might befal them, if they had ſo bad a Conſcience, whatſoever mental Refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations they may uſe.</p>
            <p n="8">8. That, if it may pleaſe you, the Honourable Houſe of Commons, Firſt to command to ſeize unawares, not only, all the aforeſaid Acquittances, Catalogues and other Papers, but even all the Contracts and other Papers, wherein all the aforeſaid great Summs of Money, or a part thereof may be mentioned; which ſaid Acquittances, Catalogues, Contracts and other Papers, may be found, either in the Conſiſtorial Chambers, or other places of the aforeſaid two Churches; or in each Houſe, Chamber, Cloſet, or other places of the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, Miniſters and Church-wardens of the ſaid two Churches, eſpecially in the Houſes, Chambers, Cloſets, and other places belonging to Sir <hi>John Chardin,</hi> Mr. <hi>Lecoc,</hi> Mr.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:135389:9"/>
               <hi>Blancard,</hi> Mr. <hi>La Sale Monginot,</hi> Mr. <hi>Renu Both,</hi> Mr. <hi>Frontin,</hi> Mr. <hi>Louvigny,</hi> Mr. <hi>Dugas,</hi> Mr. <hi>Braguier</hi> Secretary, Mr. <hi>Satur, Brocas, Lamote, Primeroſe,</hi> and <hi>Pioſett,</hi> which ſaid Gentlemen were all formerly, or ſtill are, the chief of the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, or ſome of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt favourers of their Party: In all probability, by this eighth means, the aforeſaid great Fund will be more eaſily diſcovered, in Caſe the ſaid Gentlemen have not been forewarned of it, as they have been of ſeveral things contained in theſe humble Remonſtrances.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That, if it may pleaſe you, the Honourable Houſe of Commons, to Command Mr. <hi>Canche,</hi> formerly Sir <hi>John Chardin</hi>'s Secretary; Mr. <hi>Galliſſard</hi> now <hi>Mr. Blan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>card</hi>'s Secretary, and all other the ſaid former <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, or preſent Secretaries, to appear in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon before the aforeſaid Honourable Commiſſioners, and and being put to their Oath declare whatever they may know about all the Summs of Money that are in the <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners Hands, and belong to the ſaid Poor Refuges, that they know off: There is no doubt but the aforeſaid Diſcovery of the aforeſaid great Fund, will be made very ſpeedily by this ninth means.</p>
            <p n="10">10. That, if it may pleaſe you, the Honourable Houſe of Commons, to order all the Bankers and Merchants, both <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> which are in the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> or in the Suburbs thereof, and in all other Trading Towns of this Kingdom, to reveal before the aforeſaid Honourable Commiſſioners, all the Summs of Money given to them, or others, that they know off, by the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, or by the ſaid Miniſters and Church-wardens of the ſaid two Churches, or by their Agents: This tenth means certainly will produce a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:135389:10"/>wonderful good Effect, in Relation to the aforeſaid Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of the aforeſaid Fund.</p>
            <p n="11">11. That, if it may pleaſe you, the Honourable Houſe of Commons, to publiſh, that every Perſon or Perſons who will Diſcover and Reveal any Summs, either great or ſmall of the aforeſaid Fund, ariſing from the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Charities and Legacies, beſtowed upon the aforeſaid Poor amongſt the Refuges, and put into the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners Hands, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhall Receive ſuch a Summ of Money as your Honours ſhall pleaſe to allot to ſuch a Perſon, or Perſons, for his or for their Diſcovery and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealing of ſuch a Summ of the aforeſaid Fund: This eleventh means will be one of the moſt Effectual ones, whereby the ſaid great Fund will be found out.</p>
            <p n="12">12. That, if it may pleaſe you, the Honourable Houſe of Commons, to Reward every Perſon or Perſons, who through his or their great Care, and ſtrict ſearch, ſhall have diſcovered, and evidently, proved that that ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, Miniſters and Church-wardens of the ſaid two Churches, have upon the ſaid great Fund ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled in the aforeſaid City of <hi>London,</hi> or in ſome other Towns of this Kingdom, any Manufactures, or given ſome part of the ſaid Fund to any Shop-keepers to make the beſt of it, or made any other uſe of it: This twelfth means alſo ſeems a very fit expedient to make appear that the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, and the ſaid Miniſters and Church-wardens of the ſaid two Churches, have ſtill the ſaid great Fund in their own Hands, or in the Hands of other Men.</p>
            <p n="13">13. That, if it may pleaſe you, the Honourable Houſe of Commons, to Force the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, Miniſters and Church-wardens of the ſaid two Churches, preſently to give, to the aforeſaid Honourable Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:135389:10"/>an exact Catalogue of all the <hi>French</hi> Refuges who have received ſomething of the ſaid Charities; which ſaid Refuges went from <hi>England,</hi> or are Dead, or imployed in the ſaid <hi>England;</hi> preciſely telling when the ſaid Poor Refuges went from <hi>England,</hi> or when they Dyed, or where imployed in the ſaid Kingdom, or at leaſt, telling how long it is ſince the ſaid Poor Refuges were not Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved at all: You, the Honourable Houſe of Commons, by this thirteenth means will be ſure, that the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> have not always well diſcharged their Duty, nor their Commiſſion; And beſides, they have in their Hands a conſiderable Fund, coming from the aforeſaid Charities, beſtowed upon the Poor <hi>French</hi> Refuges.</p>
            <p n="14">14. That, if it may pleaſe you, the Honourable Houſe of Commons, to Order ſome <hi>French</hi> Refuges that came from ſeveral parts of <hi>France,</hi> of whatever Degree and Character they may be, preſently to appear before the aforeſaid Honourable Commiſſioners, and candidly De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that they Know, or do not Know, all the aforeſaid <hi>French</hi> Refuges, to whom the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, Miniſters and Church-wardens of the ſaid two Churches, ſay they have given ſomething of the aforeſaid Charities: To Order again, all the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Refuges that came from ſeveral parts of <hi>France,</hi> of whatever Degree and Character, freely to Declare, they Know, or do not Know the ſaid Poor Refuges, to whom the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, pretend to be ſure, they have given ſome Relief, are gone out of <hi>England,</hi> or are Dead, or have been imployed in the ſaid Kingdom, at the ſame time told by the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, Miniſters and Church-wardens of the ſaid two Churches: And to Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der moreover, that the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Refuges, who came
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:135389:11"/>from ſeveral parts of <hi>France,</hi> of whatever Degree and character they may be, to make with all ſpeed, a more ſtrict inquiry about the ſaid Poor Refuges, departed out of <hi>England,</hi> or Dead, or imployed in the ſaid Kingdom; and about what time when they departed from <hi>England,</hi> and when they Dyed, or where imployed in the ſaid Kingdom: And to make alſo a ſtrict inquiry about the ſaid Fund, and all things that concerns it: And to Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them to make a true Relation of all thoſe premiſes, to the aforeſaid Honourable Commiſſioners: This four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth means will be a Touch-Stone to try Truth, or Untruth, that hath been, or ſhall be told, by the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, Miniſters and Church-wardens in their Anſwer, and will ſhew, as all other means before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned may do, a great Fund, come from the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Charities, into the Hands of the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, Miniſters and Church-wardens of the ſaid two Churches.</p>
            <p n="15">15. That, if it may pleaſe you, the Honourable Houſe of Commons, to let the Publick underſtand, it is a very material Thing, that every Perſon or Perſons, of what Degree or Character ſoever, he or they may be, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed any private Charities, and payed any Legacies to the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, or to the ſaid Miniſters and Church-wardens of the ſaid two Churches ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, ſome ways or other, what Summs of Money their ſaid private Charities and Legacies did amount to, when and to whom the ſame were beſtowed and payed: That this fifteenth means wonderfully will Force the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, Miniſters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to give an account of a good part of the aforeſaid great Summs; And to convince even the ſame <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, Miniſters and Church-wardens, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to have in their Hands a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:135389:11"/>Fund than is neceſſary for the aforeſaid Poor Refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges Maintainance.</p>
            <p n="16">16. That if it may pleaſe You the Honourable Houſe of Commons, to know, who are the Tellers of all the Summs, gathered upon the aforeſaid three Briefs, and received by the aforeſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, and to command, the ſaid Tellers of the ſaid Summs of Money, to declare and ſhew by all neceſſary circumſtances, how many Summs they have told, and when, and to whom of the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, they have told the ſaid Summs. Again, if it may pleaſe You the Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Houſe of Commons, to underſtand more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, all the Summs of Money, gathered upon the ſaid three Briefs, and call the chief Receivers to an account for the ſame. That this ſixteenth means, will wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſerve for the diſcovery of the aforeſaid Fund, and will ſorce the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, to give a more ſtrict account of it.</p>
            <p n="17">17. That, if it may pleaſe You the Honourable Houſe of Commons, to order all the aforeſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners, to give up an exact account of the Fifteen Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Pounds lately granted by your Honours, to the aforeſaid Poor, which are amongſt the Refuges, forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to deliver to the aforeſaid Honourable Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners, all the Catalogues of Miniſters, Gentlemen, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes, and other Poor, which are amongſt the <hi>French</hi> Refuges, to whom the ſaid Fifteen Thouſand Pounds, have been, or ſhall be diſtributed. And to order, at the ſame time, all the ſaid Poor amongſt the Refuges, who ſhall be, or can be in this City, or its Suburbs, to appear in Perſon, every one, according to his Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Character, before the Honourable Commiſſioners, and all thoſe, of the ſame Refuges who ſhall be in the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:135389:12"/>Country preſently to write a Letter, to the ſame Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Commiſſioners: That by that means, it may clearly appear, whither the ſaid Catalogues are exact, or no. Again to order every one, in particular, of the ſaid Poor amongſt the Refuges, to declare, to the ſaid Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Commiſſioners, the number of the Perſons of his Family, his employments, or the way he hath to maintain himſelf and his Family, his Rents, or his Wants, his Age, his Infirmities, and thoſe of his Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And to order, that all in general, ſhould declare, upon their Conſcience and charitably, what they know, concerning the Summs of Money, or Revenues, what concerning the Poverty and Wants of others which are, or ſhould be more or leſs relieved; That by that way it may clearly appear, whether the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners, (the moſt cunning men, amongſt the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuges) have wronged ſome of the Poor Refuges, or no, in ſome thing, or other. And moreover, if the ſaid French Commiſſioners are found guilty of any wrong, to order, that all of them, appear, before your Honours, together with all thoſe, who had been wronged; That the ſame French Commiſſioners may be convinced for ever, before your Honours, that they have acted unrighteouſly. That you the Honourable Houſe of Commons wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully will perceive, by this ſeventeenth means, whether, upon this occaſion, the ſaid French Commiſſioners, have rather followed the maxims of the World, than the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical Rules; and whether they have not acted, according to the King's Will, and your Honours intent, or no.</p>
            <p n="18">18. That, if it may pleaſe you, the Honourable Houſe of Commons, to uſe all the foregoing means, or ſome others like thoſe, or ſome others better than thoſe, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:135389:12"/>to ſecond them with all your Honours power; it will certainly come to paſs, that all the ſaid Poor amongſt the Refuges, will be in a way of living contentedly, all their life-time, and by their Demands and Petitions, will trouble no more the Supreme Powers of this Kingdom, neither the Nation, publickly, nor privately: So that the ſaid <hi>John Chabbert,</hi> hoping he may ſee in a ſhort time, the ſaid Poor Refuges, in a better condition, and the ſaid Supreme Powers, the Church and the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> will reap many advantages from the better condition, wherein the ſaid Poor amongſt the Refuges, will be, God willing; He ſhall make bold ſtill, to propoſe to your Honours, theſe following Motives, and humbly ſheweth.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Diſcovery of the aforeſaid Fund, concerns very much the King, upon three ſeveral Accounts; 1. Upon His Sacred Perſon, 2. Upon His Revenues, 3. Upon His Armies.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Upon the King's Sacred Perſon, who by the ſaid Diſcovery of the ſaid Fund, happily, and for ever, will be deliver'd from a great many troubleſome Petitions, that oftentimes may be preſented to His Majeſty, by the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, under Colour of a great Poverty of a great many <hi>French</hi> Refuges, as was done heretofore, which Poverty, without doubt, the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, very Maliciouſly, Barbarouſly, Covetouſly and Proudly occaſioned, and do ſtill occaſion. And again, the King's Sacred Perſon, by the ſaid Diſcovery of the ſaid Fund, hereafter will be free from the Care, that His Majeſty hath taken, ſo Tenderly and Piouſly to Relieve the Poor which were, and ſtill are, amongſt the <hi>French</hi> Refuges in their urgent neceſſities, for which Poor the <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners were continually a Begging; But
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:135389:13"/>to whom after they received the ſaid Relief from His Majeſty, and from this generous Nation, publickly and privately, the ſaid French Commiſſioners have given but a very ſmall matter, in compariſon of the aforeſaid great Summs, come to their Hands, cauſing them to live in Poverty, to have always a need to Begg for the ſaid Poor amongſt the Refuges, and by that unlawful way, increaſe the aforeſaid Fund (I do not know for what;) And all thoſe ſhall be proved, by the Diſcovery of the ſaid Fund.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Upon the Account of the King's Revenues, ſome whereof, beſtowed upon the ſaid Poor amongſt the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuges, during the ſpace of many Years, will be hereafter ſpared for ever, by means of the ſaid Diſcovery, of the ſaid Fund, fit to maintain all the ſaid Poor, all their Life time.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Upon the Account of the King's Armies, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into, by the means of the ſaid Diſcovery, of the ſaid Fund, many <hi>French</hi> Gentlemen, both young, or, at leaſt, Stout, and not being paſt bearing Arms, to whom, without doubt, the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Commiſſioners, have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly allowed, and do ſtill allow, very good yearly Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, as clearly will be ſeen by means of the ſaid Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, of the ſaid Fund, will be foreced to chuſe to go into the Armies, if a good part of their ſaid Penſions, as it muſt be taken away from them, which ſaid part of the ſaid Penſions, in all appearance, cauſeth the ſaid young and ſtout French Gentlemen Refuges to forbear taking up Arms, by that means, the young and ſtout French Gentlemen Refuges, not only do not ſerve the King nor the State at all; But even are burdenſome to both. Again, the ſaid young and ſtout French Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen Refuges, unhappily to ſpend their time, either in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:135389:13"/>Idleneſs, or in Divertiſement, in Playing, ſometimes in Slandering and Evil-ſpeaking, or in ſome kind of Riot and Debauchery. Moreover to which ſaid Armies, many of the French Refuges of whatever Degree, will alſo be eaſily induc'd to chuſe to go, if ſome part of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of the ſaid Fund, when it ſhall be diſcovered, be beſtowed to maintain well all their Life time the Officers and Souldiers, who have been, or hereafter ſhall be mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the King's Service, in the ſaid Armies.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the ſaid Diſcovery of the aforeſaid Fund ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much concerns this State of <hi>England,</hi> in general and particular.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In general, becauſe the ſaid State, in general, by the ſaid Diſcovery of the ſaid Fund, every Year, not only may ſave a conſiderable Summ of Money, Charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and Piouſly granted to the ſaid Poor amongſt the Refuges, by your Honours; But alſo, may imploy the ſaid Summ in paying ſome of the Taxes, laid upon the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and granted to the King for the maintainance of his Armies by Sea and Land, and by this, or other means, eaſe all the People.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In particular, becauſe many Perſons, Members of the ſaid State of <hi>England,</hi> having been very often Solli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited, either by the troubleſome Demands of the ſaid French Commiſſioners, or by the earneſt Requeſts of the ſaid Poor themſelves, to ſpare ſomething for them, and the ſaid Perſons, thereby moved to ſpare ſomething for the ſaid Poor Refuges hereafter will be no more obliged to ſpare any thing for them, when the ſaid Fund ſhall be diſcovered, whereof the product, undoubtedly, will be ſufficient continually to maintain all the ſaid Poor Refuges,</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:135389:14"/>
            <p n="3">3. That the Diſcovery of the aforeſaid Fund, which is in the French Commiſſioners Hands, concerns very much the Church of the aforeſaid State, in general and particular.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In general, becauſe 'tis certain, by the Diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the ſaid Fund, the whole Body of the Church of <hi>England</hi> will be partaker of the Prerogatives, Conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies and Benefits, which without doubt will be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Inhabitants of ſome Hamlets, Villages and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Towns in the ſaid State of <hi>England,</hi> which ſaid Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants have no means to keep a Miniſter Reſident in their Hamlet, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> when ſome French Miniſters, Refuges who are already, or may be in time, very well acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue, ſhall be granted to the ſaid Inhabitants of the ſaid Hamlets, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which ſaid French Miniſters, all their Life time, will be maintained with the product of the aforeſaid Fund, in exerciſing their Miniſtry in the ſaid Hamlets, Villages and Little Towns, under the aforeſaid Church of <hi>England</hi> Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In particular, becauſe the aforeſaid Inhabitants, of the Hamlets, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Church of <hi>England</hi>'s Members, which have no means to keep a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Reſident in the ſaid Hamlets, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Diſcovery of the great Fund, will take poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of one of the greateſt Advantages in this World; if ſome French Miniſters, Refuges, maintained by the product of the aforeſaid Fund, are granted to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the ſaid Hamlets, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by the Diſcovery of the ſaid Fund, and the conveniency to enjoy the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of ſome French Miniſters, making their Reſidence in the ſaid Hamlets, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and being maintained with
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:135389:14"/>the product of the ſaid Fund, will have no more the trouble to be expoſed to many grievous miſchances.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Often to be expoſed, to be a long while, without they can make their Children be Chriſtened, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to ſee them dye, before they can be Baptized, for want of convenient time of doing it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Upon many occaſions, to be expoſed, to the hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no comfort, when they are lying Sick, ſometimes when they are dying, and at a great many other oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities, whereof the Comforts and Prayers, ſaid by a Miniſter are of great importance.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To be expoſed, to a great many fatigues, eſpecially in the Winter time, when publickly to call upon God, and be inſtructed about their Religion, or to make their Children be Chriſtened, or to deſire the Prayers of the holy Congregations, for their ſick Perſons, the ſaid In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the aforeſaid Hamlets, Villages, and little Towns, muſt go to other Towns and Places from their Habitations, one, two, three, nay, and ſometimes four Miles, and ſometimes farther, when it rains, ſnows, freezeth, and the wind bloweth very hard, which ſaid Toils may diſhearten oftentimes the ſaid Inhabitants of the ſaid Hamlets, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and keep them from their publick Chriſtian Duty.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That the aforeſaid Diſcovery of the aforeſaid Fund, particularly concerns very much, many <hi>French</hi> Miniſters, Refuges, which were not in Orders in <hi>France;</hi> but which have received Holy Orders, from the Hands of the Right Reverend Fathers in God, and Lords, Biſhops of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Church of <hi>England;</hi> becauſe the ſaid Miniſters, having now no ſettlement at all, or having but an inconſtant one, ſhall have one, or one durable, upon the account of the ſaid Diſcovery of the ſaid Fund, a part of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:135389:15"/>whereof, muſt, according to the Rules of Juſtice, be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon the ſaid Miniſters, as well as upon all other Miniſters, Refuges maintainance, which were admitted into Orders in <hi>France,</hi> ſeeing that the ſaid French Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, Refuges, who have received Holy Orders from the Hands of the ſaid Right Reverend Fathers in God, and Lords, Biſhops of the ſaid Holy Church of <hi>England,</hi> at leaſt, are Miniſters and Refuges, by as good a Title, as all the ſaid other French Miniſters admitted into Orders in <hi>France</hi> can have, eſpecially when the ſaid Miniſters, admitted into Holy Orders in <hi>England,</hi> by God's Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, and that of the ſupreme Powers of this Kingdom, and Heads of the ſaid Holy Church of <hi>England</hi> appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, will be ſettled in the ſaid Hamlets, Villages and little Towns, whereof the Inhabitants cannot maintain a Miniſter, to exerciſe their Holy Miniſtry, and reſide there all their Life-time.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That the aforeſaid Diſcovery of the aforeſaid Fund, concerns very much, many particular <hi>Engliſh</hi> Miniſters, and that upon two Accounts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe hereafter, when all the French Miniſters Refuges ſhall be no longer in this World, or in <hi>England,</hi> the Inhabitants of the aforeſaid Hamlets, Villages, and Little Towns, who cannot maintain a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, wherein the aforeſaid Miniſter's Refuges, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed their Miniſtry, for a yearly allowance, taken out of the ſaid Fund, hereafter, for ever may enjoy the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilege of having, either an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Miniſter, or a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, come from French Parents, born in <hi>England,</hi> to whom allowance taken out of the product of the aforeſaid Fund, being granted; becauſe there is not any part of a Civil Law, more juſt than that which preſcribes, that, if the Done deceaſeth before his giver,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:135389:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Gift muſt be given again to the ſaid giver: So that, then the aforeſaid French Miniſters, and all other French People fled for Refuge into <hi>England,</hi> who are here the Dones, being deceaſed, or being no more look'd upon, as ſurviving all his Dones, after that, they may beſtow their Beneficence upon whomſoever they pleaſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe it being poſſible, that the aforeſaid Fund every day might be increas'd, if the ſaid Fund was put into the hands of ſome laborious, diligent, and ingenious Perſons, who beſides, may be very zealous for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion in general, and in particular, for the Holy Church of <hi>England</hi>'s Intereſts. In time, God wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, ſome <hi>Engliſh</hi> Miniſters, maintained with ſome part of the aforeſaid product, taken from the ſaid increaſed Fund, may be granted to the Inhabitants of all the Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, Villages, and little Towns of the aforeſaid State of <hi>England,</hi> who for want of competent means to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a Miniſter Reſident in their ſaid Hamlets, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> may have one, and in all likelyhood could never have had any, but by the aforeſaid ways.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That, the aforeſaid Diſcovery of the aforeſaid Fund, concerns very much, all the Poor amongſt the French Refuges; but eſpecially, all the Poor maimed Soldiers, all the Old Poor Perſons, all the Grave, Modeſt Widows, all the Poor Orphans, all the Infirm and Weak Perſons, and all the Poor Perſons of whatſoever Age, Degree, and Rank they may be off, if by their own means, they cannot maintain themſelves, neither their Families; and that upon five Arguments.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe, by the Diſcovery, of the aforeſaid Fund, More Revenue than is requiſite, for all the ſaid Poor amongſt the Refuges, will be found out.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:135389:16"/>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe, without doubt, to ſome of the ſaid Poor Refuges, a durable, inſtead of an inconſtant allowance, will be granted, and to ſome others, a competent one too.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe, thoſe of the ſaid Refuges, who never can obtain, either any allowance at all, or but a competent one, from the aforeſaid French Commiſſioners, which being inexorable, upon every occaſion, have proteſted ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, they had no Fund at all, and ſometimes that they had one, but very ſmall and ſcanty, ſcarce capable to ſupply all the ſaid Poor Refuges, with any relief, or but even with a competent relief: And all that very ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guouſly, and by way of amphilology.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Becauſe by the ſaid Diſcovery of the ſaid Fund, it will appear, that the ſaid French Commiſſioners, have allowed, and do allow great Penſions, to many of the aforeſaid Refuges of both Sexes, which will come to be, either utterly, or partly deprived of the ſaid great Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. They will come to be deprived of them. 1. Ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly, if the ſaid Refuges are convinced, to have other competent Revenues beſides, for their Maintenance, or ſome means, whereby, it is clearly demonſtrated, that they may ſupply all their own wants, or eſpecially, if it appears, that the ſaid Refuges, of both Sexes, have ſpent, or doth ſtill ſpend, a good part of their Penſions in Luxury, both of Cloths and Diet, in Playing, and in any exceſs, or if it appears, that the ſaid great Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions cauſe the ſaid Refuges, to live in Idleneſs and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpending their time, and they become unprofitable Members to the Publick, and to the Private: The ſaid Refuges, will come, but in part to be deprived of the ſaid great Penſions, if they can prove they want relief: So that the ſaid Refuges being utterly, or in part deprived of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:135389:16"/>the great Penſions, as occaſion ſerves, and as it ſhall be thought fit, the aforeſaid Poor Refuges, may be more relieved, than they were before the ſaid Diſcovery of the ſaid Fund.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Becauſe, by the Diſcovery of the aforeſaid Fund, well managed and improved, many Poor Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, of both Sexes, who want imployment, and look for ſome, to maintain themſelves and their diſtreſſed Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, may be put upon Buſineſs, and in a way of living with their Families.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That the Diſcovery, of the aforeſaid great Fund, concerns very much the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Poor; Becauſe the aforeſaid <hi>French</hi> Poor Refuges, Living upon the product of the aforeſaid Fund, found out; and ſo being no more relieved by the Perſons of Quality, and Rich People of this Kingdom, the ſaid <hi>Engliſh</hi> Poor will Receive ſome Charities a great deal more from the ſaid Perſons of Quality, and Rich People. And moreover, that all <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as well as <hi>French</hi> Poor, may be put upon Buſineſs and live with their Families, upon the account of the ſaid great Fund, well managed, and ſeveral ways increaſed; Is what the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid <hi>John Chabbert</hi> heartily wiſheth to the ſaid <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Poor, and continually offers up his Vows to the Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent God; that it may pleaſe His Wiſe Providence to proſper his undertaking, for His Eternal Glory; For the Furtherance and Strengthening of the Kingdom of His belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Son, <hi>Jeſus Christ;</hi> For the Immortal Memory of the Honourable Houſe of Commons; For all good Peoples Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication; And for all the aforeſaid French Commiſſioners, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Conviction, Shame and Confuſion, So be it.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <hi>Hîc opus hîc Labor est, ſed Labyrinthus non est.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:135389:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
